Texas Inaugural Committee:
Texas State Library and Archives Commission
Inaugural Committee Perry-Dewhurst inaugural records
2002-2003
Texas State Archives
Texas Inaugural Committee.
Records of the 2003 Texas Inaugural Committee document its organization and planning of the inaugural ceremony for Governor Rick Perry and Lieutenant Governor David Dewhurst on January 21, 2003 and other celebratory events occurring both before and after the swearing-in of the chief executive of the state and the lieutenant governor, who also serves as Constitutional President of the Texas Senate. Types of records include minutes, agenda, meeting materials, organizational charts, schedules, lists of duties and responsibilities, invitations, tickets, badges, programs, oaths, plans, timelines, memoranda, estimates, photographs, and press releases dating 2002-2003.
0.67 cubic ft.
Restrictions on Access
None.
Technical Requirements
Researchers are required to wear gloves provided by the Archives when reviewing photographic materials. Researchers wishing to access digital versions of these records on CD-ROM must contact the Archives' Preservation Officer to obtain the necessary equipment.
Agency History
The functions and activities of the Texas Inaugural Committee are governed by Section 401 of the Texas Government Code. No later than the tenth day after the date of each election for governor and lieutenant governor, the secretary of state issues a proclamation stating who, in the secretary's opinion, based on the best information available, are the governor-elect and lieutenant governor-elect. The secretary of state then delivers certified copies of the proclamation to the individuals named in the proclamation. The governor-elect and lieutenant governor-elect then each file with the secretary of state a signed instrument. In that instrument, the governor-elect designates one individual to serve as chair of the inaugural committee and one individual to serve as a cochair of the committee; the lieutenant governor-elect designates one individual to serve as a cochair of the committee. The governor-elect and lieutenant governor-elect may appoint other members to the inaugural committee as they consider necessary.
After the committee members have been appointed, they convene at a time and place designated by the chair, take the constitutional oath of office, and hold an organizational meeting to make arrangements necessary for conducting ceremonies and events to observe the inauguration of the governor and lieutenant governor. The committee may hold subsequent meetings at times it determines or on the call of the chairman, who, when present, presides at the meetings. The committee may adopt rules to govern its proceedings. Committee members serve without compensation but may be reimbursed for actual and necessary expenses incurred in the performance of committee duties as provided by legislative appropriation. The committee may employ staff or engage the services of consultants to assist in its work, and may request the cooperation of an agency or official of state or local government.
The inaugural fund is a special fund in the state treasury to be used only for costs related to the inauguration. The comptroller credits to the inaugural fund a pro-rata share of the interest received from the deposit of state funds as if the inaugural fund were a constitutional fund. A person may contribute funds, services, or other things of value to pay the expenses of or otherwise provide for an inauguration; such contributions may be made to the inaugural committee or secretary of state. The contribution is not a political contribution for purposes of state law regulating political contributions or prohibiting a contribution by a corporation or labor organization. If the secretary of state receives a contribution while the inaugural committee exists, the secretary of state delivers it to the committee. If the secretary of state receives a contribution at any other time, then s/he transmits it to the comptroller, who deposits it in the state treasury to the credit of the inaugural fund. The secretary of state retains the receipt for the contribution in his/her office for at least four years and maintains an index of the receipts, arranged alphabetically by contributor, showing the date of the contribution, the name and mailing address of the contributor, and the amount of each contribution. The index and receipts are public information.
Money appropriated from the inaugural fund may be used for: printing; the employment of staff; the lease of office space and payment of utility expenses; professional and consultant fees; postage, telephone, and telegraph expenses; payment of expenses incurred by committee members; and any other public purpose reasonably related to conducting inaugural ceremonies and related events, including expenses of raising funds. Contributions received by the committee and not deposited in the state treasury may be expended for any purpose the committee considers appropriate. A voucher for an expenditure from the inaugural fund must be approved in writing by the chairman. The committee maintains a record of each expenditure of nonappropriated funds containing the following information about each expenditure: the name and address of the entity to whom the expenditure was paid, the amount, the date, and the purpose of the expenditure.
No later than June 30 of the year in which the inauguration is held, the committee files with the secretary of state a final report verified by a certified public accountant that shows: the total amount of contributions received by the committee, including contributions paid to the secretary of state during the committee's existence; the total amount of expenditures made by the committee from nonappropriated funds; and the total amount of nonappropriated funds remaining in the committee's possession. This report is public information. On the day the committee files the final report, the committee must deliver all unexpended nonappropriated funds it possesses to the comptroller. The comptroller deposits the funds in the state treasury to the credit of the inaugural fund. When the secretary of state determines that the committee has complied with these requirements, the secretary issues a proclamation to that effect. The committee is dissolved on the day after the date the proclamation is issued.
The 2003 inauguration was funded entirely through corporate and private underwriters and ticket sales, using none of the $100,000 allowed by state statute to cover inaugural expenses.
The 2003 Texas Inaugural Committee was chaired by Pamela Willeford, with co-chairs James Huffines and Drayton McLane. Scott Caven and Colleen McHugh were the finance co-chairs. The theme for the inaugural festivities for Governor Rick Perry and Lieutenant Governor David Dewhurst was One Star. One Future. One Texas.
(Sources include: V.T.C.A., Government Code, Section 401.001-011; press releases found within these records.)
Scope and Contents of the Records
Records of the 2003 Texas Inaugural Committee document its organization and planning of the inaugural ceremony for Governor Rick Perry and Lieutenant Governor David Dewhurst on January 21, 2003 and other celebratory events occurring both before and after the swearing-in of the chief executive of the state and the lieutenant governor, who also serves as Constitutional President of the Texas Senate. Types of records include minutes, agenda, meeting materials, organizational charts, schedules, lists of duties and responsibilities, invitations, tickets, badges, programs, oaths, plans, timelines, memoranda, estimates, photographs, and press releases, dating 2002-2003.
The first series, Planning documents, comprises records created by the Committee in organizing the inauguration, with the exception of photographs. Appointments to the Committee by the governor-elect and lieutenant governor-elect are included in the records, as is a printed version of the Committee's website which offered event information to the press and public. Planning contributions from the Texas Legislative Council are found in the swearing-in material. In addition to the inauguration itself, events for inaugural sponsors, participants' guests, and the public included a Texas Celebration at the Bob Bullock Texas State History Museum, a morning prayer service on the day of the inauguration, a barbecue on the Capitol south lawn, an inaugural parade on Congress Avenue, and the inaugural ball at the Austin Convention Center. Follow-up materials contain the only Committee meeting minutes in these records and look ahead to reserving accommodations for the 2007 inauguration.
The second series, Photographs, consists of 354 digital photographs on CD-ROM, the majority of which show only set-up and arrangements prior to the inaugural events taking place; and color 4"x6" prints made of 78 of those digital photographs which were taken during the events and which show key participants, including Governor Perry and his family and Lieutenant Governor Dewhurst. Selection of digital photographs to be printed was made by State Archives staff.
Organization of the Records
The records have been organized by State Archives staff into two series:
Planning documents, 2002-2003, 0.47 cubic ft.
Photographs, 2003, 0.2 cubic ft. (78 color prints and 1 CD-ROM)
Index Terms
The terms listed here were used to catalog the records. The terms can be used to find similar or related records.
Personal Names:
Dewhurst, David, 1945- --Inauguration--2003.; Perry, Rick, 1950- --Inauguration--2003.
Subjects:
Governors--Texas.
Document Types:
Minutes--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2003.; Organizational charts--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2002-2003; Schedules (time plans)--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2002-2003; Lists--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2002-2003; Invitations--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2002-2003; Tickets--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2002-2003; Programs--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2002-2003; Oaths--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2002-2003; Press releases--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2002-2003; Plans (drawings)--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2002-2003; Photographs--Texas--Governors--Inaugurations--2003
Functions:
Planning inaugural activities.
Related Material
The following materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the agencies and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Texas State Archives
Texas Inaugural Committee, Bush-Perry inaugural records, 1934-1999 (bulk 1998-1999), 0.47 cubic ft.
Texas Inaugural Committee, Bush-Bullock inaugural records, 1994-1995, 0.47 cubic ft.
Texas Inaugural Committee, Richards-Bullock inauguration records, 1932, 1963-1991, 3.24 cubic ft
Texas Legislative Council, Legislative Council inaugural planning documents and other material, 1955-2003, 0.24 cubic ft.
Viriginia Whitten Papers, 1973-1994, 0.94 cubic ft.
Texas Secretary of State, Inaugural fund filings, 1979-1983, 1986-1987, 1990-1991, 0.24 cubic ft.
Accession Information
Accession number: 2003/177
These records were transferred to the Archives and Information Services Division of the Texas State Library and Archives Commission by the Texas Inaugural Committee on July 2, 2003.
Other Formats for the Records
All of the documents in the first series, Planning documents, also exist as digital files on CD-ROM, in Windows 2000 Microsoft Word, Excel, or PowerPoint formats; or in Adobe Acrobat 6.0. All 354 photographs in the second series, Photographs, exist as JPEG digital image files on CD-ROM.
Detailed Description of the Records
- Planning documents, 2002-2003, 0.47 cubic ft.
  In planning the 2003 inaugural events, the Texas Inaugural Committee conducted research into past Texas inaugurals and kept records to document the committee members' decisions on each aspect of the events, including the printing of invitations and credentials, selection of vendors, detailed timelines, transportation arrangements, and financial expenditures. Types of records include minutes, agenda, meeting materials, organizational charts, schedules, lists of duties and responsibilities, invitations, tickets, badges, programs, oaths, plans, timelines, memoranda, estimates, photographs, and press releases, dating 2002-2003. The committee's publicity efforts are shown through its press releases and its public website, which was printed in its entirety. Planning contributions from the Texas Legislative Council are found in the swearing-in material. Plans made by the committee for the 2007 inaugural include contracts for hotel and convention center space and services.
  Arrangement
  These records are listed in their original order as received from the agency.
  Restrictions on Access
  None.
  Technical Requirements
  Researchers wishing to access digital versions of these records on CD-ROM must contact the Archives' Preservation Officer to obtain the necessary equipment.
  - Introduction, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Background research, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Memos and agreements, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Committee appointments and meetings, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Printing, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Staff, 2002 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Credentialing, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Timelines, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Governor's Mansion, 2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Texas Celebration, 2002 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Prayer Service, 2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Swearing-in, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Barbecue, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Luncheon, 2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Program, 2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Parade, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Ball, 2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Elected officials, 2002 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Friends and family, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Finance, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Communications (including press releases and Committee website), 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Commemoratives, 2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Transportation, 2002-2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Baskets, 2002 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Invitations and ticketing, 2002 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Follow-up, 2003 (Box 2003/177-1)
  - Inaugural committee planning documents, 2002-2003 (Box CD/DVD Box 1)
- Photographs, 2003, 0.2 cubic ft. (78 color prints and 1 CD-ROM)
  The Texas Inaugural Committee documented the 2003 inaugural events through 354 digital photographs saved to a CD-ROM to record the appearance of their arrangements for this state occasion attended by thousands of people. The majority of these digital photographs, taken before and during the inaugural ceremony, barbecue, parade, and ball show only set-up and arrangements prior to the events taking place. About one-fourth of the photographs were taken during the events as they occurred and show key participants, including Governor Perry and his family and Lieutenant Governor Dewhurst; color 4"x6" prints were made of 78 of these photographs, selected by State Archives staff. If known, names of individuals and organizations appearing in the photograph are noted on the reverse of the print.
  The digital image files on the CD-ROM are in their original order as received from the agency. The selected prints made from the digital images are listed in order according to the chronology of the inaugural events.
  Researchers are required to wear gloves provided by the Archives when reviewing photographic materials. Researchers wishing to access digital versions of these records on CD-ROM must contact the Archives' Preservation Officer to obtain the necessary equipment.
  - Inaugural swearing-in ceremony, barbecue, parade, and ball photographs, 2003, [354 digital image files on CD-ROM] (Box CD/DVD Box 1)
  - Inaugural swearing-in ceremony photographs, 2003, [17 color prints 4"x6"] (Box 2003/177-2)
  - Inaugural parade photographs, 2003, [44 color prints 4"x6"] (Box 2003/177-2)
  - Inaugural ball photographs, 2003, [17 color prints 4"x6"] (Box 2003/177-2)